Where is the surgical instruments kit
that the professor gave us?
-There is a scalpel over there.
-Berlin has got it.
The surgeons! Go and steal
the instruments from them. Hurry!
-Okay.
-Wait! Wait!
Give him the note, please.
SATURDAY
06:31 PM
33 HOURS INTO THE ROBBERY
What?
Sometimes on TV there are people like you.
Like me, like what?
Robbers.
But you don't look like one.
I can tell this isn't your thing.
Why?
The way you hold the rifle.
I thought you were the ambassador's
daughter, and not Rambo.
Well, my father always wanted
to have a son
and since I was five years old
he’s been taking me shooting.
Shooting? What at?
At sticks in the funfair?
At wild hogs, red deer,
antelopes...
But what my father would like
is to hunt ecologists.
But I don't like guns.
Once, in Norwich...
the rifle of my father's friend went off.
I saw everything.
The shot in his back,
the people screaming...
It's like...
when you see an accident on the road
and it gets stuck in your head, the...
blood stain.
Anyway...
It's not loaded, okay?
Don't be scared.
What do you think, doctor?
Will I make it?
The bullet is located...
in the clavicle.
It's not touching any vital organs
and I can't see any...
bone fragments.
No one is going to die from this.
Let's get going.
"Denver had no time for diagnoses."
-Anaesthesia.
-"Mónica was losing a lot of blood.
If he didn't take the scalpels soon,
having spared her life would be in vain."
What kind of anaesthesia will you use?
In this cases like this it's better
to use total sedation.
No.
Better to use local anaesthesia.
So my friend and I can chat
during the surgery, can't we, Arturito?
Relax, relax.
Okay, okay, that's it.
And that clock, what's it for?
To control the duration
of the local anaesthesia, 25 minutes.
If anything should go wrong
during the surgery,
we should give him one more dose.
Show the clock on the screen.
"That operation was scheduled
and had to last exactly 25 minutes
as the inspector had ordered.
That countdown would allow two
police officers wearing face masks of Dali
inside the factory
or, if it went wrong, two dead bodies
inside the ventilation ducts."
Drop the fucking rifle.
It's not loaded,
drop it before I get really pissed off.
The bullet in the breech.
Suárez, do you read me?
Duct clear.
"We're moving towards the target."
Turn around
and put your hands behind your head.
Now!
So.
What now? Not so tough now, are you?
Move, for fuck's sake, move!
Shoot now.
You fucking crazy little girl.
On your knees!
Scalpel.
Stop, stop, stop.
It’s me who gives the arms out here.
Scalpel.
You nailed it earlier on,
didn't you, Arturo?
Changing your wife's name.
Of course, it's normal.
Fornicating in the mornings with Mónica,
spending the afternoons with Laura...
It's normal to get confused.
But I love them both.
That’s the truth.
When you're in my situation,
it's very easy to judge. Everyone...
thinks you're a scoundrel,
a son of a bitch.
Far be it from me,
to make moral judgments.
I can understand everything.
You can talk freely
about anything with me.
But, in fact I’m a wretch,
a poor man who is in love with two women
and who hasn't got the guts,
to choose one of them.
“And in the middle
of that infidelity declaration,
Denver got the scalpel he needed,
and the love note Mónica
had thrown into the sea was lost
or almost because Nairobi,
always paying close attention
to any detail, spotted it."
-What the fuck did you do that for?
-I don't know, I'm sorry.
I'm sorry.
To the ground!
-You're 11 metres from the entrance.
-"Copy that."
We're proceeding.
Fucking little spoiled brat!
-I'm sorry.
-Shut the fuck up!
Don't tell me your life story, okay?
I'm not the fucking friend
of the outcast, understood?
If you go around begging for
your kidnapper's friendship,
you're so screwed.
Do you know what...?
I'm only six weeks pregnant and...
I'm more concerned
about the kid's life than my own?
You need more than an infection
to stop children
from taking on the world, my dear.
Listen, what's your name?
Moscow, they call me Moscow.
Listen, Moscow,
and what's it like...
being...?
I mean, being a parent.
Being a parent...
You see, being a parent means that
all of a sudden a pile of problems
falls right on your shoulders
and also for the rest of your life.
In a few words,
being worried for the rest of your life.
First, it's the baby's colds.
That means you'll be
in the emergency room every weekend
instead of going for a drink.
I don't mind, I don't drink.
You don’t know what you’re missing,
you don't know how good a Pacharán feels
when you leave him
there sleeping like an angel in his cot.
And then there's school.
The fear...
that all parents feel of...
your son being the dummy
and the punching bag in his class.
I mean, what’s known as "bullying" now.
The fact is that in my case...
it was my son who did the beating.
He was being expelled all the time.
I can’t tell how many schools
he went to, that...
And then his mum, poor her,
she had her bad habits...
Well, not that poor?
She dumped me there, on my own...
Soldiering.
Because in the end, all you want is...
him to be normal,
him not to end up
on a corner, smoking joints
instead of going to school.
But being a parent...
is good. It's very...
Hey, no, no! Mónica, stay with me!
Look at me, look at me!
Stay with me, darling.
-Come on, look at me!
-Dad!
-That's it.
-What's wrong?
-Nothing, it's okay.
-Yes?
-Her temperature is too high.
No, don't stop looking at me.
Let's see, look at me, that's it.
I've got everything with me.
"Five minutes left
for the doctors to come out."
Copy that.
It’s out.
Thanks.
And now you stitch him up.
Who, me?
Yes, you.
You're a nurse, aren't you?
-Yes, I am.
-So, then.
It's local anaesthesia.
We put it on the wound
and in a jiffy... no pain.
Yes.
Come on, allow me, I'll do it.
-You keep checking her pulse.
-Right.
There we go...
Done, now, that’s it, that’s it.
Do you know what I'm going to do
when... I get out of here?
I'm going to study long-distance.
You haven't studied in your whole life.
I'm not saying that I'll study medicine,
but I'll...
take it up where I left it, you know?
This is going to hurt a little more, okay?
Look, look. Oh!
Done.
Right, done.
-Ready.
Now, in five minutes
it'll start working and...
we'll start to open up, okay?
-Come on.
-Ready.
-You're within two metres of the entrance.
-We can visualize the target.
Let's see...
I'm not feeling well.
I think I'm going to be sick.
Are you a nurse, a ballet dancer?
What the fuck is wrong with you?
I'm a nurse,
but I'm not used to working
surrounded by guns.
Right, that's enough. I'll stitch him up.
But I want everyone to remain silent
please.
Come on, start.
Tweezers.
The Professor wants to speak to you.
All right. Take the nurse
to the toilet so he can vomit.
If he doesn't, put his head
inside the loo until he does it.
Do you hear me? Until he does.
Good bye, Arturo.
Come on.
Walk.
They're broadcasting on short wave
and it's encrypted, so they're getting in,
-but I don't know from where.
-Copy, I’m moving to plan B.
"Okay and get the medical team
out of there right now."
Now.
"My darling, be strong. I'm fine.
I love you. Mónica."
"Sub-inspector Ángel knew
in less than a second
that they had lost another battle.
Those sinister masks
meant that they’re going to throw
two men in at the deep end.
Also that the guy
who had planned that robbery
was smarter
and had more imagination than the police,
the CNI and the Intervention Unit,
and when they're well ahead of you,
it's time to run."
We have to leave now.
Miss, excuse me, we're done here.
Can we go now, please?
-Yes.
-Yes?
Calmly.
You, follow me.
Doctor, doctor!
Just one moment.
One minute, 30 seconds.
-What's wrong?
-They have frequency inhibitors.
Suárez, do you copy?
They've installed frequency inhibitors.
I think communication will be lost.
"Do you read me?"
There are frequency inhibitors.
We're losing communication.
Suárez.
How did the surgery go?
Well, but we should come back in 24 hours.
Thank you for your interest,
but, for the post-op
we have enough qualified people.
My friend, the nurse...
Are you feeling better now?
-Yes, yes, thanks.
-I'm glad to hear.
Excuse me if I can't see you off,
but I leave you in good hands.
Good bye.
-Good bye.
Give our regards to the people outside!
-Did you tell Arturo that I'm fine?
-Sorry?
Did you tell Arturo that I'm alive?
-Yes. No... I didn't tell him.
-Did you or you didn’t?
I gave him the note.
And what did he say?
Damn, he was overjoyed. He was overjoyed,
what was he supposed to say?
-That...
-Go on.
That...
-That he loves you very much.
-What else?
He said that...
That when you two get out of here,
he's going to take you to Australia.
To Australia?
Yes.
I can't see it.
He also told me that he doesn't know
what you saw in him to like him.
-To Australia?
-Yes, Australia.
It's his wife's dream destination.
Besides, Arturo knows
I'm scared of flying.
What happened?
His wife went in with the doctors?
-Has Laura been here?
-No.
-Yes.
-He told her on the phone.
-Suárez!
-Command post, do you read me?
Command post, do you read me?
Shit.
Inspector, the surgeons are coming out.
Don't stop.
Run, run now. Run now. Run now! Hurry!
"Come on, out!"
Ángel is running in.
Something’s gone wrong.
Cancel! They've changed their face masks.
They're not wearing the Dali ones.
They're going straight to their slaughter.
What?
Listen up, do not go in.
Suárez, do you read me?
Target reached.
We're proceeding to remove the flap
and we'll be in.
What are you doing?
A bullet.
A bullet wound.
Gosh! Gosh! Gosh, Moscow!
It’s a real bloodbath!
-Move away, let me do it!
-"Then something unexpected happened.
Nairobi did her best and used
her meticulousness for the greater good.
Instead of telling on them,
she helped Moscow save Mónica's life."
I'm going to get some fresh air.
-"Or at least her leg."
-For fuck's sake!
"She really hadn't come to kill anyone."
-Damn, come on!
-"And as I told you before,
she wasn't going to let anything
screw the Professor's plan up."
Suárez, do you read me?
They have changed the face masks.
There are some interferences. Command
post, do you copy me? I can't hear you.
They're not wearing the Dali face masks!
It's a fucking suicide.
Do not go in, I repeat, do not go in!
"It's an order!"
"They have changed their masks.
They're not wearing the Dali face masks.
Attention, do you read me?
"Do not go in!"
-"We're cancelling the operation."
-Damn!
We're cancelling the operation.
Berlin, everyone can relax now.
Plan B has worked as planned.
They're withdrawing.
"Hidden behind a metallic voice
with their cameras and their strategy
negotiating a robbery,
the Professor was in his element."
At the rest of things in life
he was completely useless.
Both so different
like Clark Kent and Superman.
Perhaps because he had spent
his childhood and youth
lying on a bed at San Juan de Dios
hospital of San Sebastián
talking just with senior nurses
and reading books.
He was neither a ordinary
nor a very sociable fellow.
And not the least the seducer type."
Can I sit down?
Yes, sure.
"So I loved making him feel nervous."
So, when you're not planning a heist,
what do you do?
You mean in my spare time
or something like that?
Do you go dancing or...?
No, no, not at all. I don't have
the slightest sense of rhythm.
Have you got a girlfriend?
Married?
We agreed on no personal information.
You're not a virgin, are you?
I've been in some relationships.
Several.
Not a whole lot and they didn't last long,
but I've had a few.
Relationships... I mean...
sporadic relations.
Sporadic ones, I don't mean
with prostitutes, don't misunderstand me.
Well, I don't know, you may be gay.
For God's sake... No.
No, it just hasn't happened.
I'm not inside any closet
or anything of that sort.
People find a lot of things sexy.
Dancing, muscles, fair hair,
a French accent...
Do you know what I find sexy?
Intelligence.
Men who speak to you
and you can't help admiring them.
It doesn't matter whether they are tall,
short, ugly, good-looking...
It turns me on that they talk to me
about things I don't know.
Well, it's a peculiarity,
it's registered in dictionaries,
it's called sapiophilia.
You know everything, don't you?
Well, if you'll excuse me,
I'm going to see the blast off.
One thing.
How did you come up
with the idea of this heist?
It wasn't me who had the idea.
And who did?
It wasn't me.
That sapiophilia thing
sounds to me like fucking a toad.
-Who the fuck were those face masks of?
-I don't know.
Their mouth was open kind of,
as in distress.
Like, I can't say,
"The Scream" from Munch. That one.
Munch, the Expressionist painter!
Dali, Munch... Which will be the next one?
You don't know how happy it makes me
that you ask that question, inspector.
If you had to change it,
which painter would you choose?
Sorry... I don't know, Picasso, perhaps?
-Goya.
Velázquez.
Velázquez...
Da Vinci. Yes, with a beard.
-I like it, a beard.
-Andy Warhol.
-The soup guy?
-Andy Warhol? Ángel.
Yes, Andy Warhol,
the one who painted Marilyn.
He's a painter...
a very well-known, iconic painter.
The hair and the glasses.
Ángel, you're full of surprises.
Full of surprises
with a microphone in your glasses.
They could change the face masks every day
for a month
and we wouldn't be able
to ever be ahead of them.
But that's not the crux of the matter,
inspector, and you know it.
"But that's not important, otherwise..."
How the fuck did they know
we were inside?
How long did they spend studying
all our next steps each second?
If I'm honest with you, half of my life.
How long do they expect
to be inside there?
Not long, only 9 more days.
10, 11 the longest.
We're playing a fucking game of chess,
"and they're beating us."
But I have a Trojan horse, inspector.
You have little chance to beat me.
It's time to think carefully...
look back,
go back to the starting point.
We all know this started long time ago.
We know that those who were inside
had been there before.
We have footage of Cortés
and Oliveira entering the museum.
"But did they enter alone?
Was it the first time or the last one?
How many times did they visit it?"
Did they speak to anyone?
A sign, a look...
and, more important, did they
leave any fucking string to pull?
"I want you to go through
the CCTV footage again
and check them second by second."
The rest of us will try to rest.
Some of you haven't slept
for over 30 hours.
Suárez, give me a call
if anything happens.
You're in command.
"Affray in Marcelo Usera, any unit near?"
Please,
leave channel eight free
for the hostages crisis!
"No one uses channel eight, thank you!"
Listen, Raquel.
Fancy a bite before going home?
Between eating and sleeping,
I'd choose the former, but...
I'm worn out, Ángel.
I’m sorry, thanks.
"Have you ever thought
that if you could go back in time
you probably wouldn't make
the same decisions?
And that we all make our own snowballs
with our bad decisions,
snowballs that get bigger and bigger,
like the rock in Indiana Jones,
and slide down after you to squash you.
All the decisions we made in the past
they take us inexorably to our future.
Rio was going to realize
that as soon as he switched on
the only television set
there was left in the factory,
in case at any point we lost
communication with the professor."
Turn it on, kid!
Turn it on, see what they say about us.
This, bigger
than Glasgow Great train robbery!
"A yet unknown number
of robbers gained access...
What do the robbers want?"
This is a big one!
"Do they want to hit the system?"
My goodness!
Not even the Americans could have done it!
This is made in Spain but with M-16!
Beat it!
Gosh, my parents!
"An adolescent... a bit of a weirdo...
"Shy...
-Shy.
Our son was always locked in his room,
but we thought he was
playing computer games or...
But one never thinks
that he is a criminal.
And then... you see him on TV
with a rifle, shooting,
with 60 people all locked up.
-And you see he's like those jihadists.
-Paco...
He isn't our son anymore.
Please, don't say that.
For me... For me it's like he was dead.
But, Paco...
We have just heard the words
of one of the parents, heartbroken..."
The professor said no news from outside.
"But he had also said
he wanted a robbery with no violence,
with no victims."
Ángel, yes.
"Hello, Raquel.
Were you sleeping?"
No, no, no, what's the matter?
No, no, no, no. Nothing, relax.
Look, I’ve been thinking.
Have you got a minute?
Give her a rest, man,
she must be worn out.
Yes, sure, yes.
Sorry to be so direct:
what was all that about Andy Warhol?
-Sorry?
-"That, about being full of surprises."
What's wrong with me, I'm not supposed
to like museums or modern painters?
I'm not supposed
to like something other than the Atleti?
Yes, of course you are.
It took me by... surprise,
because I didn't know.
"The same way I didn't know
you were an Atleti supporter".
-But it suits me, doesn't it?
-Yes, it does.
Yes, it does.
Listen, Ángel, I'm really tired.
Can we speak tomorrow?
The guy I saw you with,
you were holding hands.
Would you sleep with him?
-"Tell me, I want to know."
-Ángel, what's all this about now?
Would you sleep with him, yes or no?
Answer me.
Well, yes, I would, why not?
"I'm a free, 40 year-old woman,"
and the truth is
that I could do with a good bang,
to... have something different
to think about.
So I surely would.
And, so what?
I understand.
You would give anyone a chance.
Ángel...
What happened between you and me
in Cercedilla was a fling.
"Eight years have passed and, look,"
I made a clean cut
because we're colleagues.
-And friends, Raquel.
-And friends.
-And you're married, Ángel.
-"I'm married."
Because you said
it wouldn't work between colleagues.
"Then you got married,
and on top of that with a colleague."
And because you never see me like...
a winner, you always see me
like the loser who is not...
supposed to like Andy Warhol.
"But if for a moment
you would see me as a man,"
I promise you it would take me
less than ten minutes to leave Carmen...
Forgive me. Raquel, I’m sorry. Damn,
I don't know what I'm saying, anymore.
"It's this... job,
which is driving us mad."
Yes, yes, that's true, all of us.
"Ángel, it's late. Go to bed, huh?
We'll talk tomorrow."
-Good night, Raquel.
-"Good night."
Who were you talking to?
I can't believe you were spying on me.
I couldn't help overhear the conversation.
Go to sleep, it's late.
Too late. Now, I can't sleep.
Let's see, tell me, what's wrong now?
-What?
-Two suitors.
He's not a suitor,
it's Ángel, a colleague.
Ah, I thought
you were making him feel jealous
with the stranger in the bar,
the one from the beers.
Please, mum, I wasn't making him jealous!
And you... don't close any doors.
And now that you're not married,
you can go around playing the field.
-Ah, playing the field.
-Yes, playing the field.
Of course.
Kido, in the end love is...
what makes us see life in a different way.
And you lately just see
the dark side of everything.
It may mean that
you haven't got over... all this.
Let's see, mum, let's see,
what haven't I got over, eh?
You also think I pressed false charges...
and I'm bitter because my ex
got involved with my sister
and I want to screw them?
Your husband
got involved with your sister?
Mum, what are you saying?
-What?
-Nothing. Yes...
I just wanted to play it down.
In the end that man
has hooked up with two sisters
like in the films... those erotic ones.
Mum. Mum, are you okay?
How are you getting on with the heist,
darling?
Sorry... Not well, not well. not well.
There, sitting all day,
in a stagnant situation, and... Yes.
But you sitting, my darling?
What you have to do is to chase.
You only catch bad people when
you chase them. As if you didn't know.
Good night, darling.
What a nice surprise!
You should come around more often.
I can see you have
a very cute little office.
-You already have two.
-I like offices.
I have always...
wanted to have one with a mahogany desk,
but crime and offices
don't get along.
It's so hot, isn't it?
I can see you're wearing
your bullet proof vest to come to see me.
I'd have preferred a bustier,
one of those Venetian ones.
You see?
I can't quite make you out.
Why did you come, Tokyo?
To ask you
please
to phone the professor
and tell him what you did,
that you order the execution of a hostage.
Naughty boy.
Because you know what?
The professor is my guardian angel,
and if you don't tell him,
I'll have to do it.
You?
And you'll be a tattletale.
a snitch, a filthy rat.
I'm a gentleman,
I wouldn't allow that to happen.
Yes.
I violated the first rule of the plan.
I’ve killed a hostage.
"Well not exactly me, Denver has,
but that's not important."
Let's say he did it strictly
following my orders.
I preferred to tell you myself.
It was the only red line.
You've screwed everything up.
-I understand your shock.
-"You've screwed everything up."
That woman had a mobile phone
between her legs.
She might have wanted to use it
to phone her cousin Chelito...
and tell her she was shagging the CEO,
but I actually think
she wanted to phone the police.
No more phones in the future.
You can be sure of that.
Who was she?
Mónica Gaztambide.
"Will you punish me?"
You should.
"I know you're an idealist,
that you think they will give us
the banknotes when we say please,"
that you want to be a decent guy,
while you give us guns and explosives
to blow this building up,
but no more games.
You'll have to punish me,
"because if you don't have the guts,
we won't succeed."
I've told you on and on
over the past years:
it's not me who has a problem, it's you.
"You have to punish me because
that way I'll know you are a real captain"
who is at the helm with no doubt,
that you're dependable.
"It seems you don't want
to talk about it now.
For the time being, nobody
outside knows about this demise,
so the plan is on."
They'll ask for proofs of life
in less than 48 hours.